Guide to the James E. Jackson and Esther Cooper Jackson Photographs Collection PHOTOS.221
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
James E. Jackson and Esther Cooper Jackson Photographs
1910-1995
1960-1979
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Jackson, Esther Cooper
Jackson, James E., 1914-2007
PHOTOS.221
4 boxes
James E. Jackson (1914-2007) and Esther Cooper Jackson (1917- ) are African-American communists and civil rights activists, best known for their role in founding and leading the Southern Negro Youth Congress (1937-1948). James Jackson was head of the Communist Party of the United States of America (CPUSA) Louisiana state organization in 1946, and was a Party organizer in the automobile industry in Detroit from 1947 to 1950. He then moved to New York, becoming the Southern Director for the Communist Party. In 1951 he was indicted under the Smith Act (charged with advocating the overthrow of the U.S. government), and became a fugitive until 1955. He later served as the CPUSA's Educational Director and International Affairs Secretary, retiring in 1991. Esther Cooper Jackson served as the Executive Secretary of the Southern Negro Youth Congress from 1942-1946 and co-founded and served as the managing editor from 1961-86 of Freedomways, the influential African-American political and cultural quarterly. The collection consists of ca. 1,350 items (mainly black and white photographs), the largest part of which documents or derives from the international travels of the Jacksons—primarily James Jackson's travels as a representative of the CPUSA from the1950s through the 1980s; also included are a small number of family photographs and images documenting political and organizational activities of the Jacksons from 1930s through the 1950s and some images from Freedomways, mostly documenting cultural events sponsored by the magazine. Individuals represented include CPUSA leaders and activists, as well as leaders of Communist nations.
(circa 1,350 items: 1,000 black and white prints and 250 color prints, from 1 x 1.75 to 11 x 15; 50 black and white negatives; 35 color negatives; 20 slides)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by James and Esther Jackson, 2005-2006. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 2006.002, NPA.2006.042, and NPA.2006.077
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
James E. Jackson (1914-2007) and Esther Cooper Jackson (1917- ), African-American communists and civil rights activists, are best known for their role in founding and leading the Southern Negro Youth Congress (1937-1948). Both were raised in middle-class families with histories of civil rights activism. James Jackson graduated from Virginia Union University in 1934, and at Howard University (the alma mater of his parents) graduated from the College of Pharmacy in 1937. After attending Dunbar High School in Washington D.C., Esther Cooper graduated from Oberlin College in 1938, and completed her master's degree at Fisk University in 1940, writing as her thesis "Negro Women Domestic Workers in Relation to Trade Unionism." James Jackson joined the Communist Party in 1931, and Esther Cooper joined in 1939. The couple met in 1939 (they married in 1941) when James Jackson was staying at Fisk while working for Ralph Bunche as an investigator for what would become Gunnar Myrdal's An American Dilemma: The Negro Problem and Modern Democracy(1944).
The Southern Negro Youth Congress (SNYC), a Communist-led popular front organization, held its first annual conference, organized by James Jackson and Ed Strong, in Richmond, in February 1937. Under its slogan "Freedom, Equality, Opportunity," the SNYC campaigned for the full range civil, economic, political, and social rights for African Americans. Activities and issues included, supporting labor organizing (including domestic workers), campaigns against lynching, police brutality, and the poll tax, for the right to vote and an end to segregation, for an end to employment discrimination (sometimes via consumer boycotts), and during World War II, for enforcement of regulations barring discrimination in war industries. The Jacksons played leading roles throughout the SNYC's first decade, Esther Jackson as Executive Secretary, and James Jackson as Special Projects Director, respectively. In 1939 the SNYC moved its headquarters to Birmingham, Alabama.
James Jackson entered the army in 1943 and served in the Burma theatre. In autumn 1945, Esther Jackson attended the World Youth Congress in London, where she met W. E. B. Du Bois, which marked the start of a close association the Jacksons and Du Bois. In 1946 James Jackson became State Chairman of the Communist Party of Louisiana. In 1947 the Jacksons moved to Detroit, where James Jackson began work as a Party organizer among the automobile workers, while Esther Jackson was active in the local branches of the Progressive Party and of the Civil Rights Congress, another popular front organization. In 1951 the Jacksons moved to New York and James Jackson was named Southern Director of the Communist Party. In June 1951, he was indicted under the Smith Act (charged with advocating the overthrow of the U.S. government) and went underground to avoid arrest. Emerging almost five years later, Jackson was sentenced to prison, but he did not serve time, as the Smith Act was declared unconstitutional by the Supreme Court shortly after.
Thereafter, James Jackson served as a full-time Party official, including as a member of its leading Political Bureau, and as Education Director and as International Affairs Secretary, in which capacity he traveled throughout the Communist countries and elsewhere. Meanwhile, in 1961 Esther Jackson helped found the influential African American political and cultural quarterly, Freedomways, and served as its editor throughout its years of publication, from 1961 to 1986. James Jackson retired in 1991, in the aftermath of the 1991 split in the CPUSA.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of ca. 1,350 images, mainly black and white photographs. The largest group of images documents the Jacksons' (in particular James Jackson's) extensive international travels in an official capacity for the CPUSA. These include trips as part of CPUSA delegations to international communist meetings convened in the Soviet Union. These consist almost entirely of official press photographs, including a leather-bound official presentation-type photograph album holding images from the 26th World Congress of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union, in Moscow, 1959. Originally holding thirty (mainly 8 ½ x 6 inch) black and white prints (six became loose and are stored in a folder adjacent to the album; seven images are missing), most of these consist of iconic images of Moscow cityscapes and buildings, wide shots of the Congress and Nikita Khrushchev (then First Secretary of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union) addressing it, but a few are two-shots or group shots that include James Jackson. Also documented are journeys to state-sponsored gatherings in eastern European Soviet bloc countries including Bulgaria, Czechoslovakia, East Germany, Hungary, and Poland, as well as trips to Canada, western Europe (England and France), Latin America (Argentina, Cuba, and Venezuela), Africa (Ethiopia), and Asian countries. The latter include Cambodia, China, India, Mongolia, and North Korea, but most notably Vietnam (from 1963 to 1980). The photographs from the trips to Vietnam include a small group of images of Jackson interviewing American prisoners of war (including U.S. Navy Lieutenant-Commander Richard Allen Stratton) in 1968 at the North Vietnamese detention camp known as the "Hanoi Hilton." Also notable is a 1980 color snapshot of James Jackson with Madame Binh, former leader of the National Liberation Front's delegation to the 1970s U.S.–Vietnamese peace negotiations in Paris, although most of the photographs from Vietnam appear to be official Vietnamese press photographs documenting the destruction wreaked by the war rather than private photographs.
The collection also includes images of CPUSA leaders and luminaries (portraits or shown with James or Esther Jackson or the Jacksons together), such as Eugene Dennis, Gus Hall, Elizabeth Gurley Flynn, and prominent African-American communists Louis Burnham, Hosea Hudson, Henry Winston, Bessie Mitchell, and Angela Davis, as well as photographs of W. E. B. Du Bois. Also pictured with James Jackson are international communist leaders such as Ho Chi Minh, Nikita Khruschev, Leonid Brezhnev, and Mikhail Gorbachev; Henry Winston is shown posed with Fidel Castro. In addition, images from the files of Freedomways are included in the collection. These mainly document cultural events sponsored by the magazine, which include performers such as Harry Belafonte, Ossie Davis, Pete Seeger, Miriam Makeba and Carmen De Lavallade. Also notable in this series are a small number of searing images of police pursuing and beating residents of Harlem and bleeding residents during a conflict that broke out in July 1964 following protests over the killing of an African-American man by a white police officer.
More sparsely represented in the collection are biographical and family photographs, images that relate to the SNYC, pictures of demonstrations (ranging from May Day rallies of the 1940s and 1980s to 1940s civil rights marches, protests against the war in Vietnam and an early protest against United States' intervention in Arab countries) and of delegations of African-Americans visiting government officials, including President Lyndon Johnson and Democratic Senator (and Progressive Party vice-presidential candidate) Glen Taylor of Idaho.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged chronologically within series, with the exception of series V and XIV, which are arranged alphabetically.
The files are grouped into sixteen series:
Missing Title
I. James E. Jackson.
II. Esther Cooper Jackson.
III. Esther and James Jackson.
IV. Group Pictures.
V. Photographs of Others.
VI. Communist Party of the United States (CPUSA).
VII. Communist Party of the Soviet Union (CPSU).
VIII. International Communist Parties.
IX. Conferences.
X. Miscellaneous Events.
XI. Demonstrations and Rallies.
XII. Southern Negro Youth Congress.
XIII. Freedomways.
XIV. Travel.
XV. Negatives.
XVI. Photo Album.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Communist Party of the USA Photographs (Photos #223)
James E. and Esther Cooper Jackson Oral History Collection (Oral History #57)
James E. and Esther Cooper Jackson Graphics Collection (Graphics #26).
James E. and Esther Cooper Jackson Papers (Tamiment #347)
African American communists.; Black-and-white photographs.; Communism -- United States.; Moscow (Russia); Color negatives.; Color slides.; Color photographs.; Black-and-white negatives.; Vietnam.; New York (N.Y.).; Freedomways Associates; Jackson, James E., 1914-2007; Flynn, Elizabeth Gurley; Hudson, Hosea; Stevens, Hope; Jackson, Esther Cooper; Khrushchev, Nikita Sergeevich, 1894-1971; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973; Mitchell, Bessie; Makeba, Miriam; Southern Negro Youth Congress; Nguyễn, Thị Bình, 1927-; Communist Party of the United States of America; Baez, Joan; Taylor, Glen H. (Glen Hearst), 1904-1984; Stratton, Richard Allen; Seeger, Pete, 1919-2014; Gorbachev, Mikhail Sergeevich, 1931-; Hall, Gus; Fedossejew, P. N.(Petr Nikolaevich); Ho, Chí Minh, 1890-1969; Du Bois, W. E. B. (William Edward Burghardt), 1868-1963; Dennis, Eugene, 1905-1961; De Lavallade, Carmen, 1931-; Davis, Ossie; Castro, Fidel, 1926-2016; Burnham, Louis E.; Brezhnev, Leonid Il'ich, 1906-1982; Davis, Angela Y. (Angela Yvonne), 1944-; Mitchell, Charlene, 1930-; Belafonte, Harry, 1927-; Jackson, James E., 1914-2007; Jackson, Esther Cooper
- Series I: James E. Jackson.
  - Childhood, 1910s, 1931 (Box 1A, Folder 1)
  - Drawings by, 1968 (Box 1A, Folder 1a)
  - Drawings of, 1975-1978, undated (Box 1A, Folder 1b)
  - Drawings unidentified, undated (Box 1A, Folder 1c)
  - Family Pictures, 1920-1949 (Box 1A, Folder 2)
  - In the Army, 1943-1945 (Box 1A, Folder 3)
  - Portraits-Dated, 1946-1991 (Box 1A, Folder 4)
  - Portraits-Undated, 1940s, 1950s (Box 1A, Folder 5)
  - Portraits-Undated, 1960s-1980s (Box 1A, Folder 6)
  - Portraits from 22nd Communist Party of the Soviet Union World Congress, Moscow, 1959 (Box 1A, Folder 7)
  - Portraits from 24th Communist Party of the Soviet Union World Congress, Moscow, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Portraits from Marx Conference, Berlin, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Portraits from a Trip to Vietnam and Cambodia, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Teaching at Pratt Institute, Brooklyn, NY, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 60th Birthday Celebration, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - At Demonstrations against the Police Murder of Leon Mosley, and for Carl Winter's Release from Prison, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - The Joliot Curie Gold Medal for Peace Award Ceremony, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - With Students at an Unidentified Conference, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - With Louis Burnham, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - With Khrushchev, Brezhnev, and Gorbachev, 1960s, 1980s (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - With Elizabeth Gurley Flynn, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - With Gus Hall, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Series II: Esther Cooper Jackson.
  - Esther Cooper Jackson, 1970-1989, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Esther Cooper Jackson with W.E.B. Du Bois, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Esther Cooper Jackson with Others, 1940s, 1970-1989 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Series III: Esther and James Jackson.
  - Esther and James Jackson, 1960-1979 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Esther and James Jackson with W.E.B. Du Bois, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Esther and James Jackson-Visit to Moscow, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Esther and James Jackson with Others, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Series IV: Group Photographs.
  - Group Photographs with James E. Jackson, 1942-1977 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Group Photographs with James E. Jackson, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Group Portraits with James E. Jackson and other CPUSA members, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Group Photographs of Unidentified Individuals, 1972, 1985, 1995, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Series V: Photographs of Others.
  - Burnham, Louis, 1940s (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Davis, Angela, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Du Bois, W. E. B., 1960s, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Fedossejew, P. N., 1970s (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Flynn, Elisabeth Gurley, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Hall, Gus, 1970-1989 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Hudson, Hosea, 1950s, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Johnson, Lyndon B., President, with Unidentified African-American Delegation in the White House, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Tereskova, Valentyina, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - White, Charles, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Winston, Henry, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Winston, Henry with Fidel Castro in Moscow, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Portraits of Others (Identified), undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Portraits of Others (Unidentified), undated (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Series VI: Communist Party United States of America (CPUSA).
  - May Day, Union Square, New York City, 1960s (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Delegation to Budapest, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 50th Anniversary of CPUSA, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - CPUSA / Communist Party of the Soviet Union Delegation Meeting, Moscow, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Delegation to the 60th Anniversary of the Great October Revolution, Moscow and possibly other locations in the Soviet Union, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Du Bois Foster School of Marxism-Leninism, Mesaba Park, Minnesota, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 22nd National Convention, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - May Day, New York City, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Committee Meetings, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Delegation to an Unidentified Event, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Series VII: Communist Party of the Soviet Union (CPSU).
  - CPSU, 50th Anniversary of the Great October Revolution, Moscow, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - CPSU, 24th World Congress, Moscow, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - CPSU, 25th World Congress, Moscow, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - CPSU, 60th Anniversary of the Great October Revolution, Moscow, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - CPSU, 60th Anniversary of the Great October Revolution, Baku, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - CPSU, 26th World Congress, Moscow, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - CPSU, Unidentified Events, 1973, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Series VIII: International Communist Parties.
  - Argentina: Unidentified Communist Party event, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Canada: James E. Jackson's Address at the 30th Anniversary of Pacific Tribune (the official newspaper of Canada's Communist Party), Vancouver, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - China: Unidentified Event, 1980s (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Czechoslovakia: World Assembly, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - East Germany: S.E.D., The Socialist Unity Party's 9th Congress, Berlin, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - France: The French Communist Party Congress-with CPUSA Delegation, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Mongolia: Mongolian People's Revolutionary Party (meeting), 1987 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Poland: Polish Workers' Party Congress, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - International Communist Parties Events (Miscellaneous), undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - International Communist Parties Events (Contact Sheets), undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Series IX: Conferences.
  - International Planning Conference, Mexico City, 1930s (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - "Marxism-Leninism 1820-1970," Berlin, East Germany (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - "Karl Marx and His Time," Berlin, East Germany, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Unidentified, Berlin, East Germany, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Series X: Miscellaneous Events.
  - Memorial Meeting in Tribute to Reverend Martin Luther King, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - United Nations Events, 1968-1978 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - ZIL Auto Plant, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Unidentified Event at Madison Square Garden, New York City, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Events with James E. Jackson's Participation, 1937, 1943, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Oversize, undated (Box Shared Tamiment OS003, Folder 1)
- Series XI: Demonstrations and Rallies.
  - Right to Vote Rally, New Orleans, LA; Right toVote March, Birmingham, AL, 1943, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Protest Against U.S. Intervention in Arab countries (Pictures of James E. Jackson), 1958 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - March on Washington (Joan Baez pictured), 1963 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Anti-War Demonstration: Vietnam, Dominican Republic (Organized by the Communist Party?), Union Square, New York City, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Veterans for Peace in Vietnam, Washington D.C., 1967 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Solidarity With the Communist Party of Chile (organized by CPUSA), 1970 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - United Farm Workers, Brooklyn, NY, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Vietnam War Protest (Organized by Freedomways?), 1970s (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Peace Demonstration, New York City (Organized by the Communist Party), 1980s (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Peace Demonstration, Washington DC (Organized by the Communist Party), 1980s (Box 2, Folder 46)
- Series XII: Southern Negro Youth Congress.
  - Southern Negro Youth Congress, 1941-1946 (Box 2, Folder 47)
- Series XIII: Freedomways.
  - Cultural Events: Art Exhibitions, 1960-1979 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Cultural Events: Concerts, 1960-1979 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Cultural Events: Dance, Carmen de Lavallade and Others, 1960-1979 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Cultural Events: Performers' Headshots, 1960-1979 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Cultural Events: Theater, 1960-1979 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Friends and Associates, 1960-1979 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Front/Back and Inner Covers; Portraits, 1960-1979 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Pictures of Books and Phonograph Records related to Freedomways, 1960-1979 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Conflict between police and African American Community in Harlem, New York, during Riot of 1964 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Political Events, Undated (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - South Africa, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Contact Sheets: Miscellaneous, 1960-1979 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Miscellaneous, 1960-1979 (Box 2, Folder 60)
- Series XIV: Travel.
  - Bulgaria, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Bulgaria: At Hy Lumer's Gravestone, 1970s (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Cambodia, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Cambodia: Contact Sheets, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - China, 1988, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Cuba (photos, postcards, memorabilia), 1960, 1967, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Czechoslovakia: Prague, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - East Germany: Berlin, 1970-1989 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Ethiopia: Addis Ababa (with Stevens Hope and Charlene Mitchell), undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - France: Paris, 1975-1980 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - India, 1970s (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - North Korea, 1980-1985 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Poland (?), 1959 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Soviet Union, 1950s (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Soviet Union: Leningrad, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Soviet Union: Moscow, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Soviet Union: Moscow, 1970s (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Soviet Union: Moscow, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Soviet Union: Moscow-Memorabilia, Postcards, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - United Kingdom: London, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - United States: Puerto Rico, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - United States: Washington DC, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Venezuela: Caracas (Portrait of James E. Jackson and Group Pictures), 1971 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Vietnam, 1960s (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Vietnam, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Vietnam, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Vietnam-Casualties, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Vietnam-"A Moment of Peace"-Pictures of Cultural Events, People and Landscape, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Vietnam-Sites of War and Devastation, 1966, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Vietnam-Ho-Chi-Minh and James E. Jackson, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Vietnam-Contact Sheets, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Vietnam, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Travel-Miscellaneous, undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
- Series XV: Negatives.
  - Esther and James Jackson, undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - James E. Jackson with Others, undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Freedomways (Headshots and Performers' Portraits), undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - International Communist Parties Events, undated (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Veterans for Peace in Vietnam Demonstration, Washington D.C., 1967 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Cambodia and Vietnam (travel), 1960s (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Soviet Union: Moscow (travel), 1970s (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 3, Folder 41)
- Series XVI: Photo Album.
  - Photo Album: 26th World Congress of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union, Moscow, 1959 (Box 4)